Guide to the Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005 UA.90.F78
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Photographs, XIII.
  - World War II, 2.
    - D-Day Normandy: The Story and the Photographs
      - Published Images, 1942 - 1964 (Box Photo 7, Folder 1-12)
        - An Army M-7 Priest self-propelled, 106mm howitzer, "Big Chief," From Battery B, 42nd Field Artillery, waits to go onboard an LCT at Dartmouth, England, on 1 June 1944., 105.
          Photo number: 2-69
        - Hedgerow "plow" affixed to the front of an M-5A1 Stuart light tank., 106.
          Photo number: 2-70
        - Equipment carried by a parachutist rifleman., 107.
          Photo number: 2-71
        - Parachutist equipment for a rifle grenadier., 108.
          Photo number: 2-72
        - Emergency parachute rations., 109.
          Photo number: 2-73
        - Rear Adm. Wilkes (left) and Capt. Chauncey Camp (right) watch a dawn landing exercise at Woolacombe, England, on 31 October 1943., 110.
        - Landing craft swing out form shore, en route to Woolacombe form landing rehearsals during 31 October 1943., 111.
        - Crewmen in slickers and life vests bail frantically to clear water from a broached LCVP during the Woolacombe exercises., 112.
        - Troops splash through the surf at Woolacombe as they disembark from an LCVP., 113.
        - An Army staff sergeant and captain – both quite wet – watch impassively as the Woolacombe landings unfold., 114.
          The captain totes an M-1 carbine, and the sergeant wears an inflatable life belt – standard equipment in the landing craft.
        - An American soldier reads a signboard erected at Slapton Sands on 29 December 1943 during the evacuation., 115.
        - Street scene in Slapton Sands during the civilian evacuation., 116.
        - A young English girl during the evacuation., 117.
        - The broad beached near Slapton Sands., 118.
          Note the grassy slopes similar to those encountered in Normandy.
        - LST-322 disgorges a portion of its cargo into a Rhino ferry off Slapton Sands., 119.
        - Convoy of LCTs plies the waters off Slapton Beach, 10 January 1944., 120.
        - Black soldiers roll off a Rhino ferry and land their jeep., 121.
          The technician 5th grade at center is apparently attached directly to the 1st Army.
        - Landing practice 17 Mach 1944., 122.
        - LCI-323 at left appears to be dead in the water, while the covey of LCVPs approaches the strand., 123.
        - An L-4 Piper observation plane passes overhead after the LCVPs maker their dash for the beach., 124.
        - The landing takes place., 125.
        - An infantryman's-eye view of the beach obstructions at Slapton Beach., 126.
        - Two member s of a Navy communications unit scan the horizon out to sea for messages from the ship approaching the shore., 127.
        - (Left to right) Lt. Gen. Bradley, Rear Adm. Hall, Maj. Gen. Gerow, and Maj. Gen. Huebner consult while observing the invasion rehearsals off the English coast., 128.
        - Destroyer Thompson (DD-627) refuels from Arkansas during pre-invasion exercises on 21 April 1944., 129.
          Note the wire, or "hawser," at right securing Thompson to the battleship's port beam and refueling line at center.
        - LST-289, its stern blown away by a torpedo launched in a German E-boat attack on 28 April 1944, lies at Dartmouth, England., 130.
          An LCM is alongside.
        - LST-289's badly damaged stern., 131.
          Note the ship's steel-hulled LCVP's and the cockeyed, single 40 mm mount.
        - Battleships Texas (right) and Nevada lie at anchor in Belfast Lough., 132.
        - General Eisenhower addresses crew members on the afterdeck of Texas., 133.
        - Ike and Kirk tour Quincy at Belfast Lough., 134.
        - Anesthetist HAIc Jesse Taylor (left) concentrates on the "patient" while Capt. A. Weiland (right), with the assistance of Lt. Joseph Barbella, prepares a plaster bandage for the patient's right forearm. PhM2c. Edward Schork looks on., 135.
        - Members of the Army's 82nd Airborne Division display their skills in a demonstration jump., 136.
        - Dignitaries including Churchill and Eisenhower watch a practice parachute drop in England on 23 March 1944., 137.
        - Members of the 101st Airborne assemble a gun dropped during training exercises in Berkshire, England., 138.
        - Bombs plummet to earth from a 9th Air Force medium bomber during the railroad and bridge busting campaign., 139.
        - Bomb detonations temporarily obscure the bridge somewhere in northern France., 140.
        - 9th Air Force bombers attack yet another bride in northern France., 141.
        - Smoldering remains of an additional critical bridge., 142.
        - Lt. Gen. Patton inspects the engine of a P-51 at the 354th Fighter Group in the British Isles., 143.
          At far right is the group commander, Col. George Bickell.
        - 9th Air Force reconnaissance photo shows beach obstructions near Cherbourg one month prior to the invasion., 144.
          Note the Germans standing and, in some cases, running among the obstacles.
        - Normandy, 0140, 6 June 1944., 145.
        - Road intersection in northern France, early morning, 6 June 1944., 146.
        - Quartermaster Depot G-22 at Moreton-on-Lugg, Hertfordshire, England., 147.
        - General Depot G-23 at Histon, England., 148.
        - Lt. Col. D. MacArdle admires the handiwork displayed on the back of Sea 1c Edwin parker's jacket during the loading operations just prior to D-Day., 149.
        - Lt. Comdr. Dwight Shepler sketches an LST in the background., 150.
        - Correspondent George Hicks records interviews with men onboard an LST before the Normandy invasion., 151.
          Note the electronics gear in the foreground.
        - Men of Force B (Backup Force) line up on the docks in Plymouth, England, to commence loading operations on 1 or 2 June 1944., 152.
        - Two Force "B" LCVPs in Plymouth come alongside a larger ship to transfer their men on board., 153.
        - Assault Force "O," lying at Portland Harbor, England, readies itself on 2 June 1944 for the voyage to Omaha Beach., 154.
          Page number: 68-69
        - Members of the 116th Infantry Regiment, 1st Battalion, depart from the beach in a fully laden LCVP, bound for USS Thomas Jefferson (APA-30)., 155.
          Note inflatable life belt on soldier at right.
        - Troops transfer from an LCVP to LCI(L)-539., 156.
          Rations are piled on the LCI's deck.
        - Soldiers board an LCI(L)., 157.
          Note the AA mount.
        - Trucks destined for Omaha Beach back into LST-51 at Portland Harbor, England, on 2 June 1944., 158.
          The truck backing in is a British Bedford with American wheels.
        - View from LST-51 as it backs away from its mooring at Portland Harbor on 2 June 1944., 159.
          LST-75 is in the background at left, with a barrage balloon flying above it.
        - Laden with troops bound for Utah Beach, an LCVP approaches a nest of LCIs belonging to Task Unit 125.5.3., 160.
        - An Army captain guides vehicles assigned the Force "U" on board LCT-821 at Dartmouth, England, on 1 June 1944., 161.
          Note M-7 Priest self-propelled howitzers among the cargo.
        - An Army Field Kitchen Unit rolls onboard LST-506. Note cartoon painted on the side of the kitchen unit., 162.
          Just to the left rear of the kitchen, a sailor named "Dick" looks on.
        - Utah Beach-bound M-16 gun motor carriage boards LST-47 at Dartmouth, England, on 1 June 1944., 163.
          Note famed "quad-.50s" mount in half-track at left and the nickname "Der Fuehrer's Express."
        - View of loading from hold of LST-47., 164.
          "Der Fuehrer's Express" backs in.
        - Lying in the River Dart, LST-47 (no doubt with "Der Fuehrer's Express" safely tucked away on board)., 165.
          Page number: 72-73
        - Chaplain Meyer holds Jewish services on board Ancon, flagship of Force "O" in early June 1944., 166.
        - Catholic Chaplain Deery conducts Mass on Ancon., 167.
        - Protestant services in progress on Ancon on 3 June 1944., 168.
          Seated in the front row, Generals Gerow and Huebner seek reassurance from Navy Chaplain R. McConnell. Note V Corps patch on shoulder of man at right.
        - Catholic service on a Coast Guard-manned LCI., 169.
        - Dorthea L. Dix (APA-67) of Assault Force "O-3," Comdr. William Leahy commanding, lies at anchor on 5 June, following the postponement of 4 June 1944., 170.
          Embarking a portion of the 16th Infantry Regiment of the 1st Division, this unit would be the first in Omaha, on Beaches Fox Green and Easy Red.
        - An LCVP plies its way toward a transport on 5 June 1944 off the coast of England., 171.
        - Army Chaplain Edward Waters holds services on a pier., 172.
          Note profusion of inflatable life belts and the soldier "Jersey" wit a -drawing of a jeep on the back of his jacket in the foreground.
        - An Anglican priest pronounces a benediction upon the crew of HMCS Algonquin on 5 June 1944., 173.
          A destroyer in Force "J" of the Eastern Task Force, Algonquin was destined for the Canadian Juno Beach landings in Normandy.
        - On 5 June 1944, Coast Guard Coxswain Don Brewer finds time to send home one last letter before the invasion., 174.
          Note pictures of wife or sweetheart and the pipe tobacco on the shelf behind him and the pinup on the wall.
        - Shortly before embarking on C-47 transports, members of Col. Leroy Lindquist's 508th Parachute Infantry, 82nd Airborne Division, receive V-Mail blanks in order to send one last letter to wives, sweethearts, or the folks at home., 175.
        - Other members of the 508th check equipment at their temporary airfield at Saltby, England., 176.
        - Eisenhower talks to troops of the 101st Airborne Division shortly before their departure., 177.
          Purpose of the "23" sign on the man at right is a mystery.
        - Members of the 101st Airborne Division, with camouflage on their helmets and face darkened, read one last letter from home., 178.
        - Lt. Gen. Brereton, commanding general, 9th Air Force, bids farewell to members of the 101st Airborne., 179.
          Note the very roughly and, likely, hurriedly painted invasion stripes on the fuselage of the C-47 in the background.
        - Soldier at left in the previous picture manages a smile for the camera., 180.
        - Medical evacuation teams prepare to load up for Normandy on the evening of 5 June 1944., 181.
          Note Their Red Cross armbands and aircraft invasion stripes.
        - Army troops on board a Force "U" LCT stand ready for the ride across the English Channel to Utah Beach., 182.
        - A Coast Guard-manned LST departs from England on the voyage to Normandy., 183.
        - A convoy of LCIs sails across the English Channel toward Normandy on D-Day., 184.
          A barrage balloon protects each LCI from low-flying aircraft.
        - Heavily laden Rhine ferry RHF-3 makes the final leg of the journey toward the invasion beaches, while a Coast Guard rescue boat is in the distance., 185.
          The name "Hell's Angels" appears on the barge at right.
        - Arkansas bombards the French coastline in support of the landings at Omaha Beach., 186.
          Note the immense cloud of black smoke from the battleship's main battery of twelve 12-inch guns.
        - Bombardment in the vicinity of Pointe du Hoc, as seen from the battleship Texas., 187.
          Note the church steeple and the buildings high atop the bluffs. This village is likely St. Pierre-du-Mont.
        - Farther down the coast, an American destroyer passes between Texas and the coast line., 188.
        - Destroyer USS Harding (DD-625) stands guard over landing craft making their runs onto Omaha Beach., 189.
          Note the destroyer's main battery turned to port and the explosion in the center if the picture. Smoke rising behind the coastline lends further evidence of the bombardment.
        - Georges Leygues or Montcalm provides gunfire support for the invading troops., 190.
          A Gleaves-class destroyer in the background at left.
        - The troops go in., 191.
          Landing aircraft lumber past Augusta, flagship of the Western Naval Task Force. That Augusta's main battery is not turned shoreward was likely not a consolation to the men in the landing craft.
        - With heavy smoke on shore drifting to the east, LCC-449 and LCg-424, British vessels under the U.S. flag, lend support to the landing operations on Omaha Beach., 192.
        - Two landing aircraft, LCI-490 and LCI-496, prepare to make the last dash to the beach., 193.
          Note heavy smoke on shore.
        - LCVPs crowded with infantry from Assault Force "O-1" press toward Beaches Fox Red and Easy Green., 194.
          The LCVP at far left is from the transport Samuel Chase (APA-26)/ Note the large waves the landing aircraft churned up and the ubiquitous smoke on the beach.
        - An LCVP from Samuel Chase charges ahead despite the explosion of a hand grenade on board after a German machine-gun bullet finds its mark., 195.
        - The view from inside and LCVP heading toward Omaha Beach., 196.
          The men's attention seems to be directed at something happening off the craft's port side.
        - American soldiers of the 1st Infantry Division reopen the Western Front against Hitler's Wehrmacht., 197.
        - Somewhat later in the morning, troops disembark fro LCI-553 onto Omaha Beach., 198.
        - A portion of Assault Force "O-1" splashes ashore from landing craft onto Easy Red or Fox Green., 199.
          LCVP at left is from the Samuel Chase.
        - Troops disembark from LCU-412 via ladders on either side of bow during the afternoon of 6 June 1944., 200.
        - Soldiers wade ashore from another LCVP., 201.
        - LCI-538 unloads the Force "B" reinforcements, who started landing at about 1630 onto Omaha Beach., 202.
          Obstructions in the surf can be seen behind the troops.
        - Force "B" troops in their wet uniforms plod ashore burdened with weapons and equipment., 203.
          One of the soldiers directly in front of LCI-538 carried an M1A1 rocket launcher with flash detector attached.
        - The soldier carrying the rocket launcher has just passed to the left, as another man wearing an inflatable life belt trudges toward the camera., 204.
        - Another platoon splashes through the surf during late afternoon of D-Day., 205.
          The soldier at left has another M-1A1 rocket launcher.
        - LST-21 unloads British trucks and tanks including a Sherman nicknamed "Virgin" at left., 206.
          Note that the Royal Navy sailor on the barge at left wears same type of horizontal band on his helmet as do U.S. navy personnel.
        - Part of Assault Group "O-3," 16th Infantry regiment, 3rd Battalion, assembles on a narrow strip on the gravelly beach at Fox Green, Omaha., 207.
          This photo was taken near Colleville-ser-Mer.
        - A 3rd Battalion man, cold, wet, and exhausted, huddles under a blanket on Fox Green., 208.
          (An Army photographer named Hall took this and the next four poignant photos.)
        - Third Battalion casualties await evacuation to England., 209.
        - Five soldiers from the 1st Division, 16th Infantry Regiment, 3rd battalion., 210.
          Who would not go home.
        - An American medical officer bandages the hand of a soldier near Colleville-sur-Mer, Omaha Beach., 211.
        - An obergefreiter (corporal) from Gen. Kraiss's 352nd Division has his hand bandaged by an American captain., 212.
          The white piping on the German's shoulder straps denotes infantry.
        - American equipment litters Omaha Beach on the afternoon of 6 June 1944., 213.
        - American assault troops set up a command and information post beside a silent enemy pillbox., 214.
          Note the fragmentation damage next to the exterior of the pillbox.
        - Just out of the surf, a wounded soldier from Force "B" receives a plasma transfusion., 215.
        - Crossed rifles lie beside an American who perished on Omaha Beach in the 6 June 1944 assault., 216.
          Note the obstruction on the beach and the life belt around the soldier, who had taken shrapnel in his right leg.
        - The scene on either Fox Green or Easy Red, Omaha Beach, in the aftermath of the 6 June assault., 217.
          Bodies and a large pile of inflatable life belts are at upper right.
        - A landing craft unloads supplies (possibly from the BB Texas) for the Ranger battalions on Point du Hoc., 218.
        - U.S. Army Rangers scale the rough terrain of Pointe du Hoc., 219.
          An extension ladder is visible on the face of the cliff.
        - Rangers show off the line and ladders used to scale the heights on Pointe du Hoc., 220.
        - With his shoulder patch proudly proclaiming his status as a Ranger, the soldier at right reloads a clip for his M-1 carbine., 221.
        - Lt. Comdr. John Knapper of the battleship Texas and a companion examine a German pillbox on Point du Hoc on 6 June, possibly during efforts of that ship to resupply the Rangers., 222.
          Knapper had served aboard Texas since joining it as an ensign in 1939. Note the belted German ammunition at left and a dead Ranger covered up at right.
        - Nevada (BB-36) bombards Utah Beach with its 14-inch guns in support of the 7th Corps landings., 223.
        - Nevada's forward guns belch smoke and flame during the bombardment., 224.
          Note the camouflage paint on the gun barrels.
        - During the morning of 6 June 1944, a shell from the German counter battery fire on Utah Beach explodes on St.-Marcouf Island., 225.
          This and the next view were photographed from the heavy cruiser Quincy (CA-71).
        - Minesweepers working to clear shipping channels explode mines in the waters across Cardonnet Bank., 226.
        - Gleaves-class destroyer throws 5-inch shells into the beach fortifications at Normandy., 227.
        - Expended 5-inch/.38 caliber cartridge cases litter the deck of USS Hobson (DD-464)., 228.
        - Force "U" is under way., 229.
          Bayfield lowers its LCVPs into the water. Nevada just to the left of Bayfield.
        - Lt. Abe Condiotti, U.S. Naval Reserve (USNR), credited with commanding the first boat to hit Utah Beach about 0630 on 6 June 1944., 230.
        - American soldiers with full equipment leap into the surf and wade toward Utah Beach near Les Dunes de Madeleine., 231.
          This particular load includes a number of medics. The horizontal lozenge on the back of the helmet denotes an NCO so that the men could recognize their leaders from the rear. Handles of a stretcher protrude into the photo at left.
        - The camera looks up just as the NCOs in the previous picture exit the landing craft., 232.
          A number of vehicles have already landed.
        - Viewed form a landing craft, a weapons carrier charges ashore at Utah Beach., 233.
          Note the machine gun on the weapons carrier and the other vehicles on the beach.
        - Members of the American landing party assist survivors of a sunken landing craft., 234.
          One of the survivors at center with an inflatable life belt helps pull to shore a comrade, who looks somewhat the worse for the wear and may be wounded. An NCO and a beach landing-party member assist another survivor (left); one soldier (left center) refuses to put down his M-1 rife; and a third survivor (right) trudges ashore wearily on his own power.
        - First aid being administered to soldiers on Utah Beach., 235.
          The survivors have collapsed on the beach and are covered with blankets. The soldier still clutching his M-1 now stands off at left. Note LCM-29 unloading in the background.
        - Men of the 8th Infantry Regiment, 4th Division, move out over the seawall at Utah Beach., 236.
          Men rest or take cover behind the wall, where most have stored their equipment.
        - A German soldier with his hobnailed boots and a coverall over his uniform lies dead beside a pillbox near Les Dunes de Madeleine., 237.
        - Men of the 8th Infantry Regiment, 4th Division, occupy a French village just off Utah Beach., 238.
          The lead man is still wearing his inflatable life belt.
        - Other men of the 4th Division (probably 3rd Battalion, 22nd Infantry Regiment) occupy a farmyard near Les Dune de Varreville, two miles northwest of Utah Beach, after clearing German snipers from the buildings., 239.
        - The troopers shown above take a breather in the milk house of the same farm after clearing out snipers., 240.
        - A heavy weapons unit of the 358th Infantry Regiment, 90th Division, pauses during its advance inland from Red Beach., 241.
          The 90th Division patch on the sergeant in the foreground has been censored out. Note the German minefield sign at right. A mortar man heads the column of the left-hand side of the road. The man standing in the road behind the sergeant is part of the beach landing party, as designated by the semicircle painted on his helmet. This is a rare photo of this division on 6 June 1944. This regiment and the 343rd Field Artillery battalion were the only contingents of the 90th Division to land on 6 June 1944. The rest followed on 7-8 June 1944.
        - A Coast Guard rescue boat pulls alongside two sailors who have abandoned their sinking landing craft., 242.
          They are wearing full life vests, rather than the life belts used by Army personnel. A line goes to the sailor nearest the boat, and the second sailor waits with a rope in hand to throw out to the second sailor.
        - The second of the two sailors comes aboard., 243.
          Note the belt securing the rescuer to the boat.
        - An LCM littered with debris evacuates casualties to a larger vessel., 244.
          The seriously wounded are being loaded onto a platform that will be raised onto the deck of the transport.
        - The crew hoists the platform with casualties from the LCM on board the transport., 245.
          They are among the first casualties to be evacuated on 6 June 1944. Empty Navy litters in the foreground await the wounded.
        - LCI-85, struck by German shell fire, comes close aboard Samuel Chase to off-load casualties., 246.
        - Casualties from the invasion on board an LST hospital ship are transported back to England., 247.
          Stretcher-borne casualties await assignment to a bunk.
        - A seriously wounded serviceman sleeps while a tube drains fluid from his nose into a basin on the deck., 248.
          Photo number: 5-63
        - A buttock wound forces this glum serviceman to rest on his stomach., 249.
          Note the piping along the bulkhead of the LST.
          Photo number: 5-64
        - Four Americans of the 82nd Airborne Division enter St.-Mere-Eglise in the early morning shadows of 6 June 1944., 250.
          The sergeant at left is armed with a Thompson submachine gun, Model M-1 with a 30-round box magazine. These simplified weapons differed from the M1928 version in that they would not accept the large drum magazine so often associated with the gangster era of the 1920s and 1930s. Also the front handle was replaced by a simple wooden grip.
          Photo number: 5-65
        - A deserted street in St.-Mere-Eglise following the 82nd Airborne assault, 10 June 1944., 251.
          Photo number: 5-66
        - Two mounted members of the 82nd Airborne Division patrol the streets of St.-Mere-Eglise on 7 June 1944., 252.
          Photo number: 5-67